very generally speaking the goal or the
overall idea of cognitive
electrophysiology is to try and
understand some of the processes of the
mind like working memory or language or
sensory perception emotion to the
dynamics in the brain to computations in
the brain by studying the electricity of
the brain of the electromagnetic waves
that are produced by the brain as the
brain is producing cognition so it's
just a very very overall general goal of
cognitive electrophysiology cognitive
electrophysiology is at the intersection
between psychology or cognitive science
and neuroscience and in particular
electrophysiology so as a cognitive
electrophysiologist is useful to think
about where on this very kind of
simplistic spectrum you you lie where
where you identify yourself with are you
more in the kind of psychology oriented
side or more on the neuroscience brain
oriented side this is an important thing
to think about because it will help
guide the papers that you should be
reading and critically thinking about
and the kinds of experiments that you
will plan on doing the types of data
analyses that you should be doing and
how to best interpret your results what
kinds of theoretical or empirical
frameworks you should be using to
interpret your results this lecture will
comprise four sections I'm not going to
go into any details about any data
analyses or data interpretations but
just to give you a very brief overview
of the the main approaches that are that
are used in cognitive electrophysiology
so time domain analyses frequency domain
analyses and the sort of intersection of
the two time frequency domain and Alice
so most people when they think of
time-domain
analyses with EEG or M eg data they are
thinking about ERPs event-related
potentials these are not the only
analyses that are possible in the time
domain
there's also microstates for example in
and multiscale dynamics are fractal
based dynamics but ear Peas are
certainly the dominant form of analysis
in the time domain here you see a bunch
of single trial EEG data I believe these
are from electrode FC Zed but it doesn't
matter the number here corresponds to
the trial number and times zero this
time is in milliseconds on the x-axis
time zero is when a stimulus appeared on
the screen in front of the subject so
here you can see that individual trials
seem to be quite variable so there's
there's quite a bit of variability over
the different trials in this plot you
can see all of the individual trials
there are 99 individual trials and the
the event related potential the ERP that
the average of all these trials plotted
in black to compute an ERP it's very
simple you just take the all of the the
trial voltage fluctuations at each time
point and average them together so very
simple just sum and divide by n and that
gives you the event related potential
one of the first things that you will
notice when looking at this plot is that
the ERP is is quite a bit smaller in
magnitude compared to the single trial
fluctuations here in in gray in fact the
ear peas tend to be somewhere around an
order of magnitude smaller than the
voltage potential fluctuations of the
individual trials now there's two ways
to interpret this some people interpret
this to indicate that single trial data
is very noisy these large fluctuations
are
indicative of just a lot of noise brain
noise and measurement noise and so by
averaging over a lot of trials we can
get rid of some of the noise and focus
on the the really relevant parts of the
signal an alternative interpretation is
that many of these dynamics are in fact
signal and they are they are meaningful
relevant for understanding the cognitive
process at hand here but these are non
phase-lock toward or jittered non
time-locked
processes and are therefore lost in the
time domain averaging so here in this
plot you can see the same ERP here is
just zoomed in a bit more so you can see
the fluctuations in finer detail ear
peas have been computed since I fired as
I know since the 1950s probably or
possibly earlier as well the general
idea the kind of foundational framework
for thinking about interpreting erps is
that there is a sequence of cognitive
operations that are happening in the
brain and some of these cognitive
operations map on to the peaks or the
troughs of these these ERP fluctuations
and so whether you agree that this is an
appropriate model that there are
sequential cognitive modules that are
being activated and they map on to these
peaks and and sort of alternating
polarity Peaks in the event related
potential is is something you can think
about on your own but this is one of the
main driving ideologies behind
interpreting AR Peas this is just to
give you the reference for where I got
this figure from
so the advantages of event-related
potentials are that they are
computationally very simple it really is
just just sum and divide by n in fact
your phone could probably compute an ERP
basically as fast as a supercomputer
could there's also a decades-old very
large very rich literature on using ERPs
to try and understand and make
inferences about cognitive processes and
so this can be a very good thing there's
a very large literature in which to
embed and relate your findings some of
the disadvantages of event-related
potentials are that as I briefly
mentioned jittered and non phase-locked
activities are are lost I will in a
future video define more precisely what
these terms mean and how we can measure
and and extract these non phase-lock
dynamics for the researchers who lean a
bit more towards the neuroscience side
of the spectrum the air peas provide a
limited scope of data analysis
possibilities that might be of interest
to someone who is focusing more on the
neuroscience aspect such as
synchronization cross frequency coupling
these kinds of dynamics ERP is in
particularly the later more cognitive
components of the ERP spectrum tend to
have low signal to noise characteristics
or low statistical power this is not
mathematically necessarily the case this
is just occasionally empirically
observed there is also a kind of an
unclear link to underlying
neurophysiology again particularly for
the later components it's it's a bit
less clear exactly how these alternating
streams of polarity reversing potentials
are are produced in the brain and what
what they what the significance of those
of those ERP components is okay so now
we get to frequency domain analyses just
by way of a very brief non mechanistic
introduction to frequency domain
analyses the idea of frequency domain
based analyses is to represent and
analyze the signal not in the time
domain but in the frequency domain
probably or hopefully you have at least
some passing familiarity with how to
interpret these frequency domain plots
but just briefly you can see you so
here's the time domain this is a one
second tick mark so this is two seconds
in total and you can see that this
signal has one two three Peaks within
one second so we would call that 3 Hertz
Hertz is a unit of frequency it's it's 1
over seconds and so your three Peaks is
corresponds to 3 Hertz it's very simple
the amplitude is one that might seem a
little strange because here you see in a
time domain the amplitude of the sine
wave seems to vary between 1 and minus 1
so you might be wondering how do we get
this bar only at at 1 we will discuss in
a future video that in fact this sine
wave is best conceptualized as a
circular process that's cycling around
with a constant distance from the origin
of 1 and what you see here as going up
and down is really just a projection
onto the real axis going back and forth
like this if that sounds sort of wacky
or fantastical then then you can look
forward to the video on the Fourier
transform where I discussed this in more
detail so here's the frequency
representation this signal here is the
frequency representation of this signal
you can see it is oscillating faster and
it has lower amplitude so here it as the
the bar is at a higher frequency 8 Hertz
and the amplitude is lower at 5 Hertz
in this panel you see the some of these
two signals and with these two pure sine
waves it's fairly easy to look at this
and see that there are two sine waves
but you can already see with this very
simple example that the constituent
parts the components of this signal are
easier to identify in the frequency
domain compared to in the time domain
this advantage of the frequency domain
is much more prominent in a signal it
looks like this so this looks like a
very complex noisy signal it may be
difficult to see or to identify how many
different components are in this signal
in the time domain but in the frequency
domain it's much easier we can see that
there is one two three four sine wave
components of of the signal plus some
low amplitude broadband noise in here so
it's much easier to talk about this
signal in terms of the frequency domain
okay so how do we get to the frequency
domain we do this by something called
the the Fourier transform which was put
forth by Joseph Fourier and according to
Wikipedia this is what he looked like
the Fourier theorem specifies that any
signal can be expressed or represented
as a combination of different sine waves
each sine wave having a different
frequency amplitude and phase so we will
talk in in glorious detail in the future
about how these frequencies are created
and how the amplitudes and phases are
computed but for now you can just know
that that any signal can be expressed
perfectly it can be perfectly
represented using a bunch of sine waves
and so the very sort of general
conceptual idea of how the Fourier
transform works is something like this
so you start with a signal this is a
single trial
of EEG data so you can see the voltage
fluctuations going up and down over time
and then we take a sine wave of some
particular frequency and we line it on
top of the EEG data and now we want to
know how similar are these two time
series now similar is put in apology
quotes here because what we are going to
measure is not really something called
similarity if you think of measuring
similarity you probably think of like a
correlation coefficient in fact the
Fourier transform uses something called
it a dot product which we will discuss
in more detail in the future but you can
just think about how much of this sine
wave can you see in this or can you
detect in this EEG data snippet and
we'll call that for now you know will
kind of temporarily call that similarity
so the amount of similarity is plotted
on the y-axis and is plotted in a
position corresponding to the frequency
of the sine wave so this is one step in
getting from a time domain into the
frequency domain and now we repeat this
step for another sine wave with another
frequency and another sine wave with
another frequency and now you can see we
are constructing this this full
representation of the time domain signal
in the frequency domain again the
mechanics of all this will become clear
in a future video ok so we can do this
now for reals and get a frequency domain
representation that looks something like
this
so we can see for example that there's
so much amplitude of a 25 Hertz sine
wave that can be measured in this time
domain signal so that's very nice the
advantages of the Fourier transform are
that it was also computationally very
fast and the Fourier transform is
ubiquitous in science and engineering so
you can go to a cocktail party with
engineers and physicists and
petitions and talk about the Fourier
transform and you will all be on the
same page so that's a very nice feature
of your data analysis stream but there
are some disadvantages of a frequency
domain representation of the data the
Fourier transform the results of a
Fourier transform are easily
interpretable only for stationary data
um briefly stationary our stationarity
refers to the statistical
characteristics of the data changing or
not changing over time so stationary
time series means that these statistical
characteristics the mean and the
variance and so on are are not changing
over time but this is awkward for
Neuroscience because we know that the
brain is a highly non stationary device
in fact it is it is no understatement to
say that neuroscientists are generally
interested in the non stationarity these
transient fluctuations these kind of
bizarre changes in brain activity
resulting from the or accompanying
cognitive processes so to be clear the
Fourier transform is a perfect
representation of the data regardless of
whether it is stationary or non
stationary but the results of a Fourier
transform are more difficult to
interpret when the data are very non
stationary and we will discuss this and
all gives very specific examples of this
in the future in part this is because
the Fourier transform hides the temporal
information there's also I want to be
careful when saying this because all of
the temporal information is actually in
the Fourier transform it's in the phases
although the phases are not generally
shown but from the results of a Fourier
transform it's difficult to determine
exactly when different frequency
components are present and so if we go
back to this part we can say that there
is some 25 Hertz
component in this signal but from this
plot it is not possible to determine
whether that 25 Hertz component is
constant over time or whether there is
very strong 25 Hertz here and no 25
Hertz
signals over here or whether 25 Hertz
signal is coming in bursts
none of these temporal dynamics can be
easily ascertained just by looking at
this plot but in fact these temporal
dynamics are things that we are very
interested in as neuroscientists the
reason why the Fourier transform makes
it difficult to interpret the temporal
dynamics is that with the Fourier
transform or the Fourier transform
involves computing the dot product
that's something we will discuss in the
future between a pure sine wave so a
signal that looks like this with the EEG
data and so you can imagine that the
weighting function would be constant
over time so that's why it we we don't
really get any temporal precision with
the Fourier transform but what we would
like in neuroscience is to be able to
combine the frequencies specificity of
the Fourier transform with some ability
to extract the temporal dynamics of when
particular frequency features are
present in the data and so one of the
ways to do this is by using a time
limited sine wave or a time series that
look something like this in this case
this happens to be a more late wavelet
this is not the only way to to perform a
time frequency based analyses we will
discuss this in more depth in the future
but you can already imagine so assume
that these are zeros here that the
weighting function would look something
like this so here we are very strongly
waiting just the center and we are
ignoring any dynamics that are happening
here in the beginning and here at the
end
and so convolution involves taking this
signal and sliding it over time to to
move this waiting function here and here
and here and that allows us to extract
these temporal dynamics that are
frequency bands specific and so this is
the basic idea of a time frequency based
approach or time frequency domain
analyses we find a trade-off between
temporal dynamics and frequency
precision so that allows us to produce
plots that might look something like
this here you see time on this axis and
the x axis and frequency on the y-axis
with smaller numbers indicating or
corresponding to slower oscillations and
higher numbers corresponding to faster
oscillations and the color or the the
kind of depth in the plot corresponds to
well it can correspond to a variety of
features that we can obtain using a time
frequency based approach in this
particular example I am plotting power
converted to a decibel change from
baseline and so power refers to the the
energy in the signal and so red means
relatively higher amplitude oscillations
and blue would mean relatively lower
amplitude oscillations relative to the
pre stimulus baseline one thing that we
will also discuss in the future that is
often sometimes necessary very often
useful is some kind of a baseline
normalization here you can see a time
frequency power plot of raw power and
here you can see the exact same data the
exact same analyses except that here the
the power data were converted to a
baseline normalized scale so it's quite
a striking difference between these two
plots so in this case you would say that
converting to
or normalizing the data somehow is is is
really important for being able to
interpret the dynamics now this was a
little bit of a carefully selected
example it's not always the case that
the raw power and the baseline
normalized power are so so different
here you see another case this is the
same data set just a different electrode
being plotted I think it's Oh Rosie or a
one somewhere in the back of the head
and here of course there are differences
between the raw power and the DB
normalized power but the differences are
not so striking relative to this
particular electrode there are several
advantages of applying a baseline
normalization to time frequency based
analyses it allows you to transform all
the data to the same scales decibel or
percent change this is a numerically
interpretable scale whereas micro volts
are more difficult to interpret and and
more difficult to compare across studies
baseline normalization allows you to
disentangle task-related from background
activity and decibel normalized power is
more likely to be normally distributed
which of course is very good for
statistics particularly if you would
like to use parametric statistics such
as ANOVA's or regressions or these kinds
of statistical analyses so again these
are issues that are important and we
will go into these in more detail in
dedicated videos in the future
baseline normalization is almost always
a good idea it is not always necessary
and in fact sometimes it is specifically
not a good idea but in most cases
baseline normalization is a good thing
and should be done okay so time
frequency
based analyses or approaching EEG data
in a time frequency frame of mind has
several advantages I think arguably this
approach allows you to get as close to
the underlying nerve physiology as as is
possible with with EEG data it provides
very flexible framework for many types
of analyses which I'll talk about a
little bit more detail on the next slide
there are many so-called low-hanging
fruits this means that there are many
cognitive processes ease mental
processes that simply have not really
been very well mapped using time
frequency based analyses so there are
many opportunities for for kind of
interesting and uncharted areas in
cognitive neuroscience to be explored
time frequency based analyses are
amenable both to very strict theory
guided hypothesis testing as well as
very open exploratory data analyses so I
think it's appealing both for sort of
theoretical oriented people as well as
methodology oriented people and of
course allows you to produce some very
pretty colored plots that's it you know
it's a non scientific advantage but it's
a it's a nice thing than the last
perhaps the main disadvantage of time
frequency based analyses is that there's
necessarily reduced temporal precision
and also reduced frequency precision
this is a necessary consequence of of of
the trade-off between temporal
information and frequency information
the reason why this is the case is
something we will discuss in more depth
but one might reasonably ask whether
this really matters this reduced
temporal precision if you go on the
order of milliseconds to hundreds of
milliseconds or more often tens of
milliseconds I think our
the interpretations of the results would
not change very much in most cases
whether you had slightly better or
slightly worse temporal precision I
would also like to point out that ERP is
in particular the later cognitive
components like the P 3 and n 400 these
also have very poor temporal precision
for example P 3 is often measured as you
know the positive component peaking
somewhere between 300 and 600
milliseconds so now you're talking about
a temporal precision of a third of a
second which is in fact worse than then
some parameter spaces in time frequency
based analyses okay another advantage or
one of the advantages i've mentioned on
the last slide of time frequency domain
analysis is that it is an entire
framework that that lends itself well to
many different types of analyses for
example this is a tiny subset of all the
possible data analysis approaches that
you can take with time frequency based
analyses
there's connectivity based on phase
fluctuations power dynamics across
frequency coupling mutual information
and so on there are all sorts of spatial
transforms that in some cases these are
not specifically based on frequency
domain utilizations but they lend
themselves very well to inspection of
frequency dynamics and yeah there's a
whole laundry list of possible analysis
approaches that you can that are sort of
justifiable based on brain physiology
and and known neuro physiological
dynamics that that can be used in EEG
studies of course you know I should I'll
have a video about this in future but
it's important to keep in mind that that
analyses of EEG data should be guided
towards or restricted by
something that's known about the brain
we need to be able to link the results
of our analyses back to something that
we know is is happening in the brain so
nonetheless time frequency based
analyses I think are really a very
powerful way of thinking about way of
approaching your EEG data