we've discussed that EEG data contain or
can be represented as a sum of of many
sine waves each sine wave having a
different frequency phase and amplitude
but we also learned that there are lots
of overlapping frequencies in the EEG
signal and so how do we determine what
frequencies are present in the signal to
what extent and fortunately Joseph
Fourier gave us the answer to this
problem he gave us a way to address this
problem through the Fourier theorem
which states that any signal can be
expressed as a combination of different
sine waves each with its own frequency
amplitude and phase we also learned how
the discrete-time fourier transform
works it works by taking the EEG signal
so your data lining up or creating a
bunch of sine waves that have different
frequencies and of course as we
discussed in the previous lecture these
are complex sine waves as a real part
and an imaginary part and then for each
sine wave that's created you have to
compute the dot product which is the
point-wise multiplication between all of
the points in the eg data and the sine
wave and then you sum up all of these
points to construct a or to result in a
complex dot product from which you can
extract amplitude and phase information
and this step is of course repeated for
multiple frequencies and this allows you
to build up this frequency domain
representation of the data
fair enough this is all just a bit of
quick review what I'd like to discuss in
this video is how exactly we get to
units of Hertz and this is an obviously
important compart of frequency based
analyses but it's also a bit of a
non-trivial
part and it can be a little bit
confusing because when you looked at the
MATLAB code for implementing the Fourier
transform you may have noticed that the
hi I'm variable the the vector that we
created for time was not the same as the
time variable that's used to create the
original signal in fact the the time
variable here goes from zero to
something a little bit less than one
regardless of what the what the unit of
the original time domain signal was and
in fact the Fourier transform doesn't
even have any representation or inherent
sort of understanding of of time or
concept of of time we just called this
variable time but the Fourier transform
would look exactly the same if this
variable were time in milliseconds or
time in seconds or time in years or if
it wasn't time at all if this was space
if we were measuring fluctuations in in
wave patterns in the ocean and our unit
was meters so the Fourier transform is
always the same so the question is how
do we get from this arbitrary unit list
vector that just goes from zero to
something a little bit less than one how
do we convert those indices to a metric
that is more meaningful that we know how
to interpret and how to work with which
in our case is going to be Hertz for for
brain data analyses so this is really
the one of the main focuses of this
lecture okay so our good friend Patrick
McGoohan is back with us and he asked
for you how many frequencies will you
give us from your transform if we use
your transform the Fourier says well he
wants information of course and in
return for the information you get n
over 2 plus 1 frequencies so n is the
number of time points that we have in
the original time domain signal and now
Fourier says we get n over 2 plus 1
frequencies back when we use his
transform so what does this number mean
this may seem like a strange or
arbitrary number n over 2 plus 1 where n
is the number
time points so let's take a few minutes
to think about what this number might
mean and why it might make sense
first we'll think about what is the the
highest frequency or the fastest
sine wave that we can possibly measure
in our data so if you think about a sine
wave that has one cycle so there's a one
cycle sine wave in order to represent
this this sine wave or measure this sine
wave we need to take a theoretical
minimum of two data points so we need at
least two data points to understand that
this is a sine wave if we only had one
data point then we would have one
measurement here and one measurement
over here at the next beak and then we
wouldn't be able to determine whether
this is a fluctuating pattern or just a
straight line because the next
measurement would be here so we need a
minimum of two data points per cycle in
order to measure a sine wave in order to
extract sinusoidal information so this
is the fastest frequency that we can
that we can extract out of our data so
having two points or two measurements
per cycle corresponds to one half of the
sampling rate so that's that's where we
get the fastest frequency in Hertz is
one half of the sampling rate this may
ring a bell one half the sampling rate
it has a particular name it's called the
Nyquist frequency so yes the Nyquist
frequency is nothing super sophisticated
or complicated it's just one half of the
sampling rate okay so this is the
fastest frequency that we can get out of
our data now let's think at the other
extreme what is the slowest frequency
that we can extract out of our data so
we can think about sine waves slowing
down so here's a sine wave with a
frequency of four it doesn't matter if
these are Hertz or whatever this is just
numbers so and then a slower frequency
would be to an even slower frequency
would be one so now we can think even
slower what is the
the lowest frequency that we can think
of
turns out it's it's zero a frequency of
zero or a sine wave with with zero Hertz
this may initially seem strange you know
that there is a sine wave that has zero
Hertz but in fact a sine wave with zero
Hertz is just a flat line as you can see
here we often call this the DC component
or a DC stands for direct current is the
term from engineering from electricity
because this is a direct current and all
these would be examples of alternating
current or AC components so this lowest
frequency that we can possibly extract
from the data is called the zero
frequency or zero Hertz or the DC
component this basically captures the
mean offset of the data and I will we'll
we'll see how this works in MATLAB in a
few minutes okay so now we know the two
extremes of the frequencies we get
whenever we do a Fourier transform we
always have zero frequency that's the
lowest frequency that can be measured or
that can be defined even and then we
always have the Nyquist frequency the
Nyquist frequency is defined by the
sampling rate so whatever the sampling
rate is the highest frequency that we
can extract from the data is the
sampling rate over to okay so now when
we go from something a little bit bigger
than zero to the Nyquist frequency this
gives us our n over two and the zero
frequency the DC component gives us our
plus one so this is how we get n over
two plus one frequencies from the
Fourier transform so this on its own may
may seem sensible but this may also seem
inconsistent with what you saw in the
implementation of the Fourier transform
in MATLAB and in particular here we saw
that the sine waves are not only created
up to n over two plus one the sine waves
are created all the way up to n so here
I'm saying that we have
and over two plus one frequencies but
here when you look at the amount of code
you see we actually get n frequencies so
so what is up with this when is the deal
at this so it turns out that things are
a little bit more complicated and if you
have looked at a at the result of a
Fourier transform you probably notice
that the frequency characteristics or
the frequencies don't stop at the
Nyquist frequency they continue going up
after are going along after the Nyquist
frequency and if you have a real-valued
signal so a signal that only contains
real parts and not imaginary numbers
then you would also or you may also you
might also have noticed that the
frequencies past the Nyquist are mirror
images so whatever you see on this side
it's flipped and you see that on this
side so what's going on with these
frequencies that are actually higher
than the Nyquist frequency when I just
told you that these frequencies cannot
be measured in the signal well maybe you
think that these are like the evil
frequencies or something it turns out
they're not so bad we call them the
negative frequencies a little bit
initially of a strange concept that
frequencies can be negative but you have
to you can think about that sine waves
have not only frequency and phase and
amplitude but sine waves also have
direction and so the positive
frequencies correspond to sine waves
that go one direction and the negative
that go the other direction in in a
polar plane now for real valued signals
like EEG and LFP and mu G signals we
don't have to really worry about the
negative frequencies because the
negative frequencies are only different
from the positive frequencies if you
have a complex signal if you're taking
the Fourier transform of a complex
signal a signal and as a real part and
an imaginary part but generally in
neuroscience we only start with real
valued signals and so in this case
negative frequencies simply mirror the
positive frequencies in fact the
amplitudes get split in half between the
positive frequencies and negative
frequencies so to reconstruct the
amplitudes in your signal what you have
to do is take the negative frequencies
or take the amplitudes from the negative
frequencies and map those back onto the
positive frequencies in practice you
don't have to do any of this mirroring
stuff you just ignore all the negative
frequencies and double all the positive
frequencies so I'll show you how this
works in MATLAB in a few minutes oh I'm
gonna show you very soon okay so now we
can switch to MATLAB so here I've
created a signal this is just some
arbitrary random numbers that I just
came up with and here we take the
Fourier transform of the signal and now
we're gonna plot the signal and it's
Fourier transform so here you see the
signal and now you can already see well
first of all we don't know what the
units are right I haven't specified a
sampling rate we don't know if these are
measurements in milliseconds or seconds
or or decades so that means we also
don't know what the unit is for the
Fourier transform but what you should
see here is that these are units and
here is is somewhere in the middle and
now you can see that the positive
frequencies and the negative frequencies
are mirror image of each other so what
you see going this way is the same as
what you see going this way and the kind
of anchor point in the center is the
Nyquist frequency okay so now what I'm
going to do is just also make up a
sampling rate so I just specify that
these data were sampled at 100 Hertz
that allows us to create a or convert
these indices from from meaningless
units into into into Hertz and so here
we do that so we may say that there
our frequencies between zero and the
Nyquist frequency half the sampling rate
and the number of frequencies that we
have in between zero and the Nyquist is
n over two plus one so here is n the
length of our signal over two and plus
one and the floor here that that means
round down and that's in there just in
case the signal is an odd number of
points okay so now you can see this new
figure now we're able to convert this
into Hertz so we know that these are
time points in milliseconds and you can
see here what we saw here is the
frequency indices as just the first
index the second index the third index
now we are able to convert this into
Hertz so this is zero Hartz the DC
component and this is 7.1 Hertz and
fourteen points something Hertz and
whatever else it is okay so now I would
like to show you the how the the DC or
the zero frequency component fits in
here so here what I'm doing is creating
or computing the Fourier transform of
this signal three different times first
is the original signal and then what I
do is take the Fourier transform of the
signal after subtracting the mean offset
so I'm just yeah so here we just compute
the mean and then subtract it and here
we compute the mean and then add it so
we're now just going to add some offset
to this signal so first let me plot just
the time domain representations of these
signals so here I just compute the
inverse Fourier transform of the signal
so we get the signal back in the time
domain you can see all three of these
versions of the signal look really
similar but they're shifted a little bit
on the y-axis so that makes sense it's
the same signal in all three cases all
I've done is subtract the mean or add
the mean so it's just a shift
in the y-axis now let's see what happens
in the frequency domain so now you can
see the frequency domain representation
of all of these or these three signals
ignore the the zero frequency for now
we'll get back to that in a second all
of these components have exactly the
same Fourier coefficients for these
three signals even though they do differ
a little bit and this is actually not
just a question of of scale because if
you zoom in it actually doesn't matter
how much you zoom in Haysville always be
perfectly perfectly overlapping and this
should actually make sense because the
rhythmic components in this signal are
exactly the same whether we push the
signal up or down on the y-axis so all
of these nonzero frequencies should be
exactly the same the only way that these
three versions of this signal differ is
in the DC component or the zero
frequency component and here in
particular you can see when we demeaned
the signal when we subtracted the mean
of the signal then the DC component went
to zero so this actually makes a lot of
sense the DC component reflects the mean
offset so we subtract the mean so we
have a zero mean and then we have a DC
of zero okay so I'd like to take this
one step further and now instead of it
adding back the mean we can add just a
number like let's say 10 so now if we
run this cell again you see again these
three time series are similar in terms
of their fluctuations but the one that I
added tend to as a offset of 10 else
that's what I defined so now in the
frequency domain of course all these
nonzero frequency components are
identical but the zero frequency
component has 20 so this may seem
incongruent because you probably
expected this to be 10 because the the
the mean offset of this
is a little bit over 10 it's 10 plus
whatever the mean of this signal is so
it should actually be just over 10 so it
turns out that I cheated a little bit
here I took a bit of a shortcut here now
remember I said in the in the PowerPoint
slide that to accurately estimate the
amplitudes from the Fourier transform
you have to fold the negative
frequencies back onto the positive
frequencies which you can effectively do
just by doubling the positive
frequencies so that's what I do here so
it turns out that there's it's a little
bit more subtle than this because only
the nonzero and non Nyquist frequency
components have a corresponding or a
complimentary negative frequency
component and this should make sense in
particular for for zero there is no
negative of zero negative zero is zero
so there's no such thing as a negative
complement of zero so in fact if you
want to accurately estimate the
amplitude of the positive 3 or of the
Fourier transform you do not simply
multiply everything by 2
the really correct way to do it would be
to multiply the frequency components by
two only for the frequency components
that are between but not including the
DC component the zero frequency and the
Nyquist frequency so here I'm
multiplying all the plot all of the
frequencies by two so this is a little
bit of a lazy shortcut but I wanted to
have this in here to illustrate how this
works so you can imagine if we would not
multiply the zero frequency component by
two then this would be something just
over 10 which is accurate that's what it
should be in practice for real EEG data
analyses it's often useful to subtract
the mean component because in general
we're not really interested in the mean
offset across a larger x
so in general you will want to subtract
the the mean from your signal before you
compute the Fourier transform kind of
like what we do here in version 2 of
this signal and so in that case it's
kind of it's okay to to use this lazy
shortcut of multiplying everything by
two because if the DC potential is is 0
then 2 times 0 is still 0 so ok so now
we see that when we compute a Fourier
transform the frequencies we get are
always between 0 and the Nyquist
frequency and the Nyquist frequency is
defined by half the sampling rate so the
next question is how many points are
there between 0 and the Nyquist
frequency so this is where the N over 2
part comes in so n is the number of data
points that you have in your time series
and so the more data points you have in
your time series the more frequencies
you will get in between 0 and the
Nyquist you will never be able to get
higher frequencies than the Nyquist
unless you change your sampling rate but
if you have a few data points you might
have a frequency resolution that looks
something like this if you have more
data points you will have a higher
resolution still you only get up to the
Nyquist frequency but you have more data
points before the Nyquist frequency and
then you could have really SuperDuper a
lot of data points and then you get very
high resolution you have more
frequencies between 0 and the Nyquist
still you can see it doesn't matter how
many points you have in your time series
you can only over ever go up to the
Nyquist frequency so if the sampling
rate stays the same the highest
frequency you can reconstruct will
always stay the same and so yeah so in
MATLAB we interpret this or we implement
this as the function linspace of
linearly spaced numbers always between 0
always between the Nyquist
and going up and the number of steps
corresponds to n over 2 plus 1 I find
that this is a is a is a tricky and
subtle point and many students get
confused about the difference between
getting up to the to the sampling rate
or the Nyquist frequency versus the
number of of time points or your
frequency resolution between 0 and the
Nyquist frequency and so because this is
a tricky point so we're gonna have so
now I'll have this MATLAB simulation
that's going to I hope illustrate for
you and and show you very clearly what
this distinction is and how these relate
to each other so what we're going to do
is create the same signal using
different sampling rates of either a
hundred Hertz or a thousand Hertz or you
might also call this a kilohertz and
different time durations well either
well here we list one second ten seconds
one second but actually there's another
second added on so there's really going
to be two seconds versus 11 seconds okay
and what we are going to do is construct
a signal so here I'm just defining the
sampling rate for this iteration and the
time vector for this iteration you can
see we always start at minus one and
then we go up to whatever is specified
by this this vector up here we are going
to create a signal called a Morley
wavelet this is a real-valued Morley
wavelet we are going to discuss more
they wavelets in much more depth in the
next section of these lectures where we
talk about time frequency decomposition
but you should already be able to look
at line 94 and see that there is a sine
wave here so it's 2 pi F T and there is
a Gaussian so e to the minus T squared
over something which is 2 s squared and
this produces a a Morley wavelet ok but
for now the characteristics of the
signal don't matter we just want
something to look at so here we create
the time
version of the signal and here we create
the frequency domain of the signal or we
compute the frequency representation of
the signal and this line 98 here we are
just scale amplitude scaling the
frequency representation just to make it
easier to look at okay so now we can
plot the time domain so here's what a
morley wavelet looks like you can see
you can see the sine wave in there and
then there's the Gaussian tapering it so
that's very nice and here is the
frequency representation so the
frequency representation of a morley
wavelet is a Gaussian or I should say
the shape of a morley wavelet in the
frequency domain is a Gaussian but again
I don't want to focus on the the shape
or the characteristics of this signal
what we really want to do is compare
what happens when we make this same
signal in the time domain and the
frequency domain using these two
different sampling rates and these two
different periods of time
so first let's zoom into the time domain
signal and what you can see is that the
the signals represented by the the black
circle and the magenta stars are exactly
the same they have the same number of pi
points so the same temporal resolution
that's not surprising you see they both
have the same sampling rate and the blue
signal is follows the same same shape
but it has many more time points and is
also of course makes sense because the
sampling rate is much higher so now they
all look like they're overlapping in
this view but in fact if we were to move
this signal over you can see that the
the so the the yeah two of these signals
are only two seconds long so they stop
here at one because it starts at minus
one and the signal represented by the
magenta stars is 11 seconds long so this
goes all the way out to ten okay so
that's pretty straightforward in the
time too
now let's look at these functions again
in the frequency domain so here we see
the Gaussian again and now things look a
little bit different because now it's
the the signal represented by the the
blue dots so the blue dots are
unfortunately a bit difficult to see but
hopefully more clear in your screen the
blue dots and the black circles those
have overlapping points in the frequency
domain and what those two signals have
in common is that they have the same
length notice that they have different
sampling rates so the sampling rate of
the blue dots is 10 times higher than
the sampling rate of the black circles
or the signal represented by the black
circles but they have the same amount of
time and here in the frequency domain
they have the same resolution um but the
signal represented by the magenta star
in contrast has many more points in the
frequency domain so the frequency
resolution is much higher even though
the sampling rate is not higher it's the
amount of time that's higher so the
frequency resolution is actually a
little bit different from how it works
in the time domain so here we see that
the frequency resolution is determined
not by the not by the sampling rate but
by the number of time points by the
amount of total time that we have and
here you see also the difference between
these signals these for the two signals
that have a sampling rate of 100 Hertz
they both stop at 50 and for the
sampling for the signal at a sample that
1000 Hertz is with blue dots then it
goes all the way up to 500 Hertz right
because here is the Nyquist frequency of
the signal represented by the blue dots
and here is the Nyquist frequency 50
Hertz of these signals represented by by
these other guys okay so this is a
subtle but important points that the the
frequency resolution is not determined
by the sampling rate is determined only
by the number of time points that you
have what is determined by the sampling
rate is the highest frequency that you
can measure so 50 Hertz or 500 Hertz for
signals that were measured at a 100
Hertz or 1 kilohertz so if you find this
still a little bit unintuitive for it or
a little bit hard to grasp then I
encourage you to go through this
simulation again and try changing these
sampling rates and change the time
durations and hopefully this will start
making more intuitive sense to you so
it's an important point and you don't
want to make mistakes
in this because because if you don't get
this point then you will then there's a
risk that you will incorrectly construct
this vector of frequencies in Hertz and
then you will completely be
misinterpreting the frequency
characteristics of the data okay so now
Patrick McGoohan is still on the prowl
and he says well he accuses 4ei of being
a cool man because he gives us only the
frequency resolution that we have
available data for and but it turns out
for EA's is not such a cool man he says
he can give us more frequencies if we
want but we we don't get more precision
he doesn't give us a better precision we
can increase the resolution of the
Fourier transform but not the precision
okay and so now Patrick McGoohan
interest is piqued and he wants to know
how this works and Fourier says well
this works by something called zero
petting so now let's talk a little bit
about zero padding and the effect of
zero padding on on frequency resolution
in the Fourier transform so here we have
a signal and what we are going to do is
zero pad
signal so you can probably guess what
zero petting means it really means you
it just means that you pad the signal
with a bunch of zeros so in this case we
just tack on a bunch of zeros to the end
of the signal it's important to remember
that whenever you zero pad in the
Fourier transform you always put the
zeros at the end you don't put the zeros
in the beginning you don't intermingle
the zeros with the signal all the zeros
go at the end so this is now an
interesting concept because now we're
getting more we have more data points in
a time domain which means we are going
to get a higher frequency resolution we
can extract more frequencies between 0
and the Nyquist frequency but on the
other hand we haven't actually added any
information so there's nothing new in
this signal we're just adding a bunch of
zeros we're not getting any more
information out of the signal that we
had before in this case but we are
getting more frequencies so this is how
we can zero pad to increase the
frequency resolution of the data
although we're not increasing the
frequency precision of the data because
we don't actually have any more
information in the signal than what we
started with okay so now we can see how
this is going to work in MATLAB so what
I'm going to do now is so this is just
redefining the signal from from the
first section what we're going to do is
compute the Fourier transform of this
signal and we're going to utilize the
second input into the function f of T
and the second input is the N of the f
of T or the number of time points to use
for the end for the when computing the
Fourier transform now if you want to
zero path so this is a useful useful
input because it means that we don't
need to zero pad manually we don't need
to take our signal and figure out how
many
want to add and just add them in like
this instead we take the the actual
signal that we have measured and if we
went to zero pad we just add more
numbers to the second input so but you
do have to keep in mind that this input
is the total length of the Fourier
transform that you want to compute not
the number of zeros that you want to pad
at the end so if we were to do something
like this we see the signal is 14 points
long but here we are taking the FFT
using an N of 10 this would actually
mean that that MATLAB is going to
truncate is going to delete the last
four points of this signal so that we
get only 10 points so this is not what
we want we want the length of the signal
and then plus however many zeros we want
pad at the end okay so here we compute
the Fourier transforms of these three
well it's the same signal but just with
different 0 padding here I define the
frequencies vector now here I'm not
specifying what the time unit is we we
don't know how to convert this into
Hertz so instead I'm just leaving these
frequencies vectors in terms of a
fraction of the sampling rate so that
means we always go from 0 and now here
we're going to stop at 0.5 which is half
of these sampling rates so now we don't
need to worry about units and you can
see that what's going to differ between
these three frequencies vectors is
whether it comes from the length of
signal 1 signal 2 or signal 3 okay so
first let's plot these signals in the
time domain and again we're plugging in
the time domain by taking the inverse
Fourier transform so you can see that
the signals are all exactly the same for
the first 14 points and then one of the
signal stops here the other signal will
be 0 padded 10 times or sorry we 0
padded
ten zeros that stops here and then the
third signal where we zero padded with a
hundred zeros that goes all the way out
here to 114 so this is how it looks in
the time domain and now let's take a
look at the frequency domain so here in
blue is the Fourier transform of the
original signal so I call it the native
end so this is just an N of fourteen
this is the these are the actual
frequencies that we really truly have in
the data that we can really measure and
you can see that as we add more zeros as
we add as we increase our n the plot
looks a little bit smoother going up to
where we get n plus one hundreds over
zero petting by 100 here it actually
looks quite pretty if we have this nice
smooth function and it seems like
they're these kind of yeah very smooth
gentle hills in the in the Fourier
transform so you have to be careful when
interpreting this because it's very
tempting to interpret this signal here
as being the you know one point seven or
point one seven frequency component of
the signal but it's the interpretation
this point is a little bit more subtle
because we do not actually measure this
component in a signal in fact this
component does not exist in our signal
because we don't have enough time points
this is just an estimate this is the
Fourier transforms guess at what this
component in the signal might be if
there were actually data at that at that
frequency if we add enough time points
so you can also see it looks very smooth
in fact it is it is a sinc interpolated
signal and in fact this is one of the
ways of sinc interpolating a signal just
by taking the Fourier transform with a
higher and this is called
I believe it's called the zero padding
theorem that describes the relationship
between zero cutting a signal
and and the sync interpolated version in
the frequency domain okay so why would
you want to zero pad the signal there
are three motivations three reasons why
you might want to zero pad your signal
during the Fourier transform one is if
you want to obtain an estimate of a very
specific frequency that you don't
natively get from the from the data
because you don't have enough time
points the second is the reason that
will be used most often for time
frequency analysis and that is to match
the lengths of the Fourier transforms
for a signal and a kernel during the
course of convolution if you don't
really understand what this means don't
worry about it we will discuss this
point when we talk about convolution in
the near future
and finally you can also zero ped just
to interpolate the results just to make
them look that smoother and a bit
prettier this is fine it's a decent
motivation but just be careful to to
interpret the results correctly because
these smoother plots are just sync
interpolated and you don't necessarily
have the ability to to MIT so these are
just estimates of what the signal at
that frequency might be if you had
enough data okay so I hope that was
useful and I hope you enjoyed seeing
Patrick go and show his face again and
look forward to seeing you in the next
lecture