if you are not very familiar or
comfortable with with looking at results
of time frequency based analyses it
might initially seem a bit intimidating
or confusing how to interpret all these
different features all these different
colors and dimensions and so here I'm
going to introduce you to kind of how to
think about how to look at results of
time frequency based analyses lest you
think that this is a kind of a
patronizing lecture then let me assure
you that these five steps that I will
introduce you to are exactly these steps
in the same order that I use every time
I'm looking at time frequency results
whether they are from my own data
analyses or if I'm reading a paper or
reviewing a manuscript so here's the
five-step plan step one is to determine
actually what is even being shown on the
plot generally the most typically shown
feature of the data to show in time
frequency plots is power this is the the
intensity or the strength of the
frequency band specific activity over
time but people will also show
connectivity results or correlation with
behavior or all sorts of things so it's
important to make sure you know actually
what feature of the data is being shown
in the plots that's the first step step
two is to inspect the ranges and the
limits of the plot so what is on the x
and y axes most of the time the x-axis
shows time and most of the time the y
axis shows frequency but that's not
necessarily the case for example
sometimes particularly in studies of of
yes sort of intracranial recordings
where they have laminar electrodes that
goes through the cortex the y-axis might
actually show depth of the cortex and
not frequency so it's important to
inspect the axes and make sure you know
what is being
plottin what is the color limit or the
grayscale intensity so this is related
to what is being shown it could be that
the color refers to power but it's
important to determine whether it's
absolute power or power relative to a
baseline and so on and then you want to
have a quick look around inside the plot
and see if any activity seems to be cut
off on the edges or maybe saturated by
the color limit so you can't really get
a full picture of what's going on in the
in the plot okay step three is to look
at the results and one of the things you
want to look for is to see if the
results are distributed in time
frequency space or if they are more
localized so this will help you in
interpreting the results and I'll give
you some examples of what I mean by this
on the next slide you should understand
what is what what are the the this what
is the subspace of the total time
frequency analysis that is being shown
in the plot if it's a time frequency
power plotted it's likely that they're
showing only the results from one
electrode or maybe they're showing only
from one frequency or only from one time
window and this is not necessarily that
the authors are trying to fool you or
trying to manipulate you into only
looking at a tiny piece of their data
it's unfortunately simply the case that
time frequency based analyses deliver a
very large and high dimensional space
and as we'll learn in the future it's
it's actually quite common to have
something like a five dimensional hyper
cube of results and we humans are
generally not very good at viewing or
interpreting these kinds of large
dimensional spaces and so we have to
take slices of these spaces so it's fine
but there should be some kind of
justifiable motivation
either based on theory or based on
previous literature or based on some
characteristics of the data that
motivates you that motivate the authors
only to show the results from one
electrode for example so it's part of
looking at the results in step 4
is we try to link the results to the
experiment design assuming that there is
some kind of task you want to know what
is happening at time zero is it a
stimulus that came on the screen or an
auditory stimulus or a button press or
some kind of response are there multiple
tasks events and how are these
represented or shown in the time
frequency plot and finally Step five is
to try and understand these statistical
procedures that are that are shown in
the plot so for example is there any
statistical special holding at all maybe
there are there is no statistical
threshold in which case the analyses
should be considered qualitative rather
than quantitative um if statistics were
performed at every time frequency pixel
our multiple comparisons issues
addressed are the analyses more geared
towards data exploration or are they
more hypothesis driven we will discuss
these differentiations in the future
when we talk about statistics but these
will will will change the how you
interpret the results okay so here's the
five-step plan now let's see how this
works in action so here we have a time
frequency plot and now we are going to
go through these five steps and and and
just sort of inspect this plot so step
one determine what is being shown on the
plot here we see it's very clearly
written in the title this is decibel
converted time frequency power and we
don't know what electrode is being shown
here but I happen to know that it's
electrode FC Zed which is a frontal
central electrode and we can see these
are so we don't know exactly what the
baseline
period is but presumably it's somewhere
around here here you can see the color
values so they its symmetric it goes
from minus 3 to plus 3 decibels relative
to baseline okay inspect the ranges and
limits of the plot so we see some of the
baseline activity which is nice here's
time zero goes up to a thousand
milliseconds and we get frequencies from
maybe like two or three Hertz up to
around forty Hertz and we can see that a
lot of the main time frequency dynamics
are contained within this time frequency
window there do appear to be some
features that are sort of leaking out
you know outside into the into higher
frequencies so it's possible that there
is some higher frequency dynamics that
we are just missing in this plot because
it only goes to 40 Hertz but so that
that's not really clear there might be
something here as well but this is
possibly if this is a a sort of fast
experiment design this might actually be
the beginning of the next trial so step
3 look at the results here we see quite
a few interesting features so there's
this kind of long ish theta response
increased relative to baseline and it
appears to be flanked by these two sort
of bursts of upper alpha somewhere
around 10 to 15 Hertz and then of course
there's this very prominent beta band
suppression from 20 to around 20 30
Hertz or so and this seems also to come
in beats and actually it looks like it's
maybe even a little something happening
before a stimulus onset okay so now we
linked the results to the experimental
design I happen to know that this plot
came from an experiment that was that
involved um cognitive control and
response conflict and in this literature
it is very typical to see theta
increases after stimulus
and corresponding roughly to the time of
the response which could be somewhere
around five or six hundred milliseconds
so this seems to fit very well into what
I know about this experiment when I know
about this literature these other
features are you know maybe the yeah
these may or may not be sort of relevant
but you know we want to kind of keep
these in mind the the reaction time the
average response time is somewhere
generally around five or six hundred
milliseconds and so some of these
dynamics might be related to the
response rather than to the stimulus per
se though it's a little bit difficult to
tell exactly from this plot just based
on on our on this plot because we don't
see their responses locked plot and
finally statistical procedures actually
there are none I see no contours there's
no kind of boxes drawn around so we
don't know exactly what is and is not
statistically significant in this plot
and so we just interpret this as a kind
of qualitative glimpse of the landscape
of activity here rather than knowing
exactly what can be statistically
evaluated okay so that was the five-step
plan and this is really what happens
inside my head when I first look at time
frequency results of course I do it a
little bit faster in my head compared to
now when I'm introducing it but if you
are new to time frequency based analyses
I recommend going through these stages
in order to understand what's being
shown to you so one of the things that
people often use time frequency based
analyses to to make inferences about is
is neural oscillations brain
oscillations and so there is a debate
that keeps coming up in literature about
whether these findings actually reflect
neural oscillations and the issue here
is that or the question is whether
a feature that you see in time-frequency
space necessarily corresponds to a an
oscillation in the way that we
understand neuro physiological
oscillations to to occur in large part
this this argument arises because of the
feature of the Fourier theorem so this I
presume is a picture of Joseph Fourier
at least according to Wikipedia this is
what he looked like
we will discuss later that the Fourier
transform is actually quite a remarkable
and powerful data analysis technique but
what the Fourier transform or what what
the Fourier transform does is allow us
to represent any signal using a
combination of sine waves and awesome
basically oscillatory processes one of
these sort of curious features of the
Fourier transform is that it does not
require that the signal is oscillatory
or even periodic the Fourier transform
as we will learn in the future is a
perfect representation of any signal so
this is Fourier giving is evil laugh
here because this the the data do not
necessarily need to exhibit oscillations
in order for in order for us to get
results that can be represented in a
time frequency power play so in this
debate if someone asks you about this is
this really a neural oscillation can you
interpret this signal this feature in
your time frequency space as in neural
oscillation I think it is very important
to make a clear distinction between two
orthogonal questions that are two
orthogonal issues that are often
confused in this discussion one question
is our time frequency based analyses
useful in analyzing EEG LFP and MHz data
and a second question which i think is
it's really orthogonal is totally
uncorrelated with
first question is is an interpretation
of an a neural oscillation appropriate
in this particular case so let me just
address these two questions very briefly
there are a few disadvantages of time
domain analyses including that any
activity that is jittered or non
phase-locked these dynamics are lost
they are invisible they're very limited
analysis possibilities such as
connectivity cross frequency coupling
event-related potentials or time domain
trial averaging often has low signal to
noise and low statistical power
particularly for the later more
cognitive or associative components so
things happening after around 150 or 200
milliseconds this is actually not a
mathematical requirement or necessity
but empirically this tends to be
observed
furthermore the these sort of
biophysical or physiological mechanisms
that produce a mere piece particularly
the later ear piece are are relatively
unclear now we can contrast these
disadvantages with advantages of time
frequency based analyses it allows you
to interpret your results in more nerve
physiologically meaningful ways as I'll
get to in a minute
and it's it provides a very flexible
framework for many types of analyses not
only time frequency power but phase
dynamics connectivity dynamics frequency
coupling dynamics there are many
so-called low-hanging fruits this means
that there are many aspects of brain
function and cognitive function that are
yet to be sort of fully charted with
time frequency based analyses so this is
useful if you are trying to make a niche
in some literature and make some new
discoveries um time frequency based
analyses are also very amenable
to strict hypothesis testing and also to
kind of open exploratory data analyses
so this is an advantage and of course
they also produce very nice colored
plots that is not really a scientific
advantage but that's okay so these are
all arguments for using time frequency
based analyses in addition to or instead
of time domain only analyses like
event-related potentials and this all of
these except I guess for this one but
these have nothing whatsoever to do with
interpreting your results in a framework
of neuro physiological oscillations
these are entirely about having a a rich
information packed signal and we want to
extract or we are using time frequency
based analyses to extract more
information than what we can get from
event related potential analysis or time
domain analyses so this is an answer to
orthogonal question number one so now
let's get two orthogonal question two is
it safe or how confident can we be about
interpreting a feature in a time
frequency plot as a neural oscillation
here the issue is that the term
oscillation in the context of
neuroscience in in the field of
neuroscience is kind of a loaded term in
the sense that there there are a number
of studied and understood biophysical
mechanisms that produce periodic
dynamics in neurons and in populations
of neurons and so when we are measuring
at the macroscopic scale even even with
an LFP so even with a micro wire that
you just is inserted into the brain but
it then is low-pass filtered to extract
sort of lower frequency components this
is a a pretty macroscopic signal
relative to the biophysical dynamics
that produce oscillations
so that that is is the the issue of
interpreting features of time-frequency
analyses as neural oscillations in my
opinion this boils down to the
distinction between a manifest variable
and a latent contract so there are
things that we presume are happening in
the brain and these are neural
oscillations and then there is the thing
that we actually measure so we cannot
directly measure all components of all
neurons so it's difficult to really
determine with a hundred percent
certainty that this thing that we see is
an oscillation but so we do the best
with the thing that we can see which is
the manifest variable so interpreting a
feature of a manifest variable in the
framework of the latent construct that
you have some theoretical motivation to
to to make this link this is actually
very similar to many other relationships
between manifest variables and latent
constructs that we see in psychology in
sociology and definitely in in cognitive
neuroscience and in neuroscience more
generally so one might also ask the
question is the fMRI bold response
neural activity or is a condition
difference in reaction time something
called attention as cognitive state
called attention in both they are in all
three of these cases we have a a latent
construct so we have something called
neural activity we have something called
attention a cognitive operation called
attention and then we have the manifest
variable which is the bold response or
reaction time or an EEG time frequency
feature and so I think this is the best
way to think about this question can we
interpret an a feature of time frequency
results as being as reflecting a neural
oscillation yes to the extent that we
treat these as manifest variables these
are measurable things
in the world and we use these in order
to make inferences about something that
is more difficult to measure directly