when you think about the human brain
probably an image comes into your mind
that looks something like this it's a
continuous sheet of folded cortex
comprising many many no one really knows
how many neurons and of course many
other types of cells however for the
remainder of your career as an EEG or m
EG researcher you should think about the
brain not as a continuous sheet
comprising neurons but instead as a
surface that contains many independent
nodes or vertices each one functionally
a modulus so let's see what this looks
like we can zoom in a little bit here
into the brain and now we want to be
thinking about the brain as comprising
functionally homogeneous you might call
these columns or hyper columns or we can
just refer to them as tubes so these are
like tubes in the brain each one is
approximately 1 to 2 millimeters in
diameter each one contains somewhere
around ten thousand to a hundred
thousand neurons and all of the neural
dynamics and neuro physiological and
biophysical dynamics that are happening
inside each of these tubes is the same
it is functionally homogeneous what's
happening inside this tube of course
this is not entirely realistic in the
real brain there is also there are all
sorts of dynamics that are happening at
a spatial scale smaller than this
however this is approximately the
smallest spatial scale that can be
measured with EEG or M eg so this is how
you should try to conceptualize the the
brain when you are interpreting your
your eg Remy G data of course if you're
measuring L FPS where you have
electrodes that are implanted inside the
brain the spatial scale can be
considerably smaller than this but this
is about the smallest spatial scale that
you can resolve with EEG or any gene
okay and each one of these tubes is
producing electrical field or my bed
fields that you measure from outside
then now typically in your experiments
you record not only from one electrode
but from many electrodes this is a
visual representation of the locations
of electrodes from a 64 electrode cap
and hopefully going into the future 64
electrodes will be seen as kind of the
minimum number of electrodes and
something like 128 or more than 200
electrodes will become increasingly
widely used and and become standard
nonetheless so here you see 64
electrodes laid out on a 2 dimensional
representation of the head this is
called a topographical plot or a
topographical map and in case you are
not familiar with interpreting these
plots what you want to do is imagine you
were looking down on the top of
someone's head and here is the left ear
and the right ear and this is the nose
and now these are the locations of the
electrodes and now what we want to do is
try to understand how or to visualize
how the activity is changing over the
entire scalp over the entire surface
so of course you the data that you
record from any one electrode might look
something like this and most of the
tutorials and lectures from from this
point on will really deal with how to
analyze and out to extract information
out of the time series that you get from
a single electrode but in practice yeah
you really want to look at the change of
activity over space as a function of
space so there are a few different ways
of representing these spatial
information that you get from EEG data
here you see probably the most
conservative visual representation so
the activity of each electrode is mapped
onto a color or in this case a gray
intensity value so here you see let's
imagine that black is mapped onto lower
levels of active
in whites is mapped on to higher levels
of activity this is a very conservative
way of illustrating the spatial
distribution of the data because we are
not making any assumptions about what
the activity might look like between
these electrodes but on the other hand
it's also a little bit difficult to
interpret this plot so by far the most
typical way to analyze or to to
illustrate the spatial distribution of
EEG data is with these interpolated
two-dimensional topographical maps and
in a few minutes we'll switch to my lap
and I will show you how to make these
topographical maps but the idea is that
we don't actually record any data from
this point here we record this is a
point that's in between these electrodes
where we actually record data but we
want to use an interpolation algorithm
to estimate what the activity would look
like at this point in this point in this
point in this point and so forth in
order to produce a smoother plot which
is easier to interpret here you see a
this same activity so actually all three
of these plots show exactly the same
data just represented in different ways
here you see the representation on a 3d
rendering of a head so there's some
advantages and disadvantages of
three-dimensional topographical plotting
versus two-dimensional topographical
blooding of course the three-dimensional
plots look much nicer they make nicer
figures and they're certainly more than
directly interpretable in terms of the
anatomical distribution of the activity
so it's much easier to see where on the
head these different features are coming
from on the other hand of course you
only see half the header or even a bit
less than half that idea so if you
wanted to show what the entire spatial
distribution of activity looked like you
would need at least two different 3d
plots and maybe even three if you had
some
if you wanted to show the activity here
all the way poster and here all the way
anterior but you would certainly need
more than one to show the entire head
two-dimensional plots in the other end
have the advantage of showing pretty
much the entire spatial distribution
from the entire head on one plot
sometimes they get cut off this a
parameter for how much of these data
coming from behind the head you you want
to show here but they show pretty much
the entire topographical distribution
but there are a little bit more
difficult to interpret in terms of the
anatomical scalp localization of the
effects topographical maps are very
important they are very powerful and and
should be used very often in particular
not only when you are inspecting your
results and showing images of your
results after you've completed your
analyses but also during pre-processing
and during the cleaning and initial
inspection of the data topographical
maps are are very powerful and you can
extract a lot of meaningful information
very quickly and so here we see two
topographical maps this one all I'm
telling you is that it's a topographical
map of the activity at 130 milliseconds
I'm not telling you anything else about
this I'm not telling you what happened
at time zero but you can already come up
with a pretty good guess just based on
looking at this plot that at time zero
there was a visual stimulus that was
presented and you might also guess that
the stimulus was presented on the right
side of the screen so in the right
visual hemifield and in fact that is
what happened in this experiment there
was at time zero a stimulus presented on
the right side of the screen this is
very useful for example if this was the
first subject in your pilot experiment
that you were testing and let's say this
is supposed to be the condition where
there was a stimulus presented on the
left side of the screen so now you know
this should raise some alarm bells that
perhaps something went wrong with the
experiment trigger coding the the
labeling of the markers or something so
it provides a bit of a sanity check
looking at these topographical maps here
you see at 400 milliseconds now again
I'm not telling you what happens at 400
milliseconds but you can probably guess
by looking at the plot that it's likely
that there was a button press maybe
there was even a right hand button press
maybe the subject press bun with the
right hand at somewhere around 400
milliseconds and that's reflected as
motor activity in fact this is what
happened in this experiment that
somewhere around 400 milliseconds there
was a response using the right hand so
already
these topographical maps are telling you
a lot of very important and detailed
information that you can use during
pre-processing to check and make sure
that the data are are good and clean and
consistent with what you should expect
based on the design of your experiment
topographical maps are also very useful
for identifying potentially bad or
artifact ridden electrodes here you see
several a series of topographical maps
the numbers here correspond to time in
milliseconds so this is a quarter second
after stimulus onset and it's very clear
it's very obvious that something is
wrong with this electrode you can see it
has very large values and they're very
different from the neighboring electrode
so we know immediately by looking at
these topographical maps that something
was wrong with this electrode so we need
to resolve this issue before going any
further with these with the data
analyses I would like to clarify two
terms that are kind of related and and a
little bit easy to confuse but they are
actually there there is an important
difference between them and the terms
are topographical localization versus
brain localization and also sometimes
called source localization the
difference between these two terms is
illustrated by these two
pictures here I apologize for the really
ugly pixelated nature of this
topographical map but it was it was very
small on the figure and I had to blow it
up anyway topographical localization is
really just an observation of where your
effect is maximal on the scalp so here
we see the effect whatever this is the
statistical map this condition contrast
is larger at this electrode than it is
at any other electrode on the scalp so
we can localize the effect to this
particular electrode as opposed to any
other electrode with topographical
localization we are not making any
assumptions we don't need any special
analyses we don't need any specific sets
of parameters we are really just
observing and commenting on where an
effect is empirically observed to be
localized to on the on the scalp that's
a different query know where in the
brain this dynamic came from where where
in the brain the source is all we know
is that it is maximal at this particular
electrode brain localization of course
we want to make an inference about where
in the brain this activity may have come
from in brain localization or source
localization does require specific
algorithms like dipole fitting or
beamforming or any other source
localization algorithm source
localization requires some assumptions
it requires several parameters so and
the inference is is different here we
are trying to make an inference about
where in the brain did the activity come
from that produced the observed scalp
topography and here with topographical
localization we are really just asking
the very simple and and and definitely
answerable question of which electrode
shows the effect the biggest okay so now
I'd like to switch to map
here if you download these sample Ichi
data and the code that that is presented
along with this video you can don't
follow along with this code so what
we're going to do here is or what I'm
going to do is introduce you to
topographical plotting basically I'm
going to let's see show you how these
kinds of topographical plots are
produced in MATLAB the first step that
we're going to do is transform the
Cartesian coordinates to polar
coordinates which is important for the
next steps once we have that we can plot
the XY locations of the electrodes and
here I'm using a function called scatter
which is very similar to the plot
function in fact you could produce
exactly the same plot with the plot
function is just sort of shown here just
for your personal edification so this
should look familiar this is just the
layout of all the electrodes this is
very similar to what I showed in the
slides except that in the slides that
was produced from an EEG lab toolbox
function that basically just plots these
electrodes plus adds some circles for
the head and the ears and the nose and
so on but this is just the electrode
locations what we are going to do next
is define points on this XY plane where
we want to interpolate the data and so
you I encourage you to play around with
this and change the interpolation detail
here I'm just using arbitrarily I just
arbitrarily picked a value of 100 as the
level of detail so we are going to
interpolate 100 points between the
minimum and the maximum of these XY
plane coordinates
those so then this function mesh grid
just converts them from a
one-dimensional array to a
two-dimensional array which is important
for the topographical plotting so here
all the black dots this is where we are
going to estimate activity so the red
dots are where we actually measured data
these black dots we don't actually have
data so in some sense or in a very
strict sense we don't actually know what
was happening on the scalp at this
location however we are going to use a
weighted combination of all these other
electrodes to estimate what the activity
would look like at this point here and
that is going to allow us to create a
topographical map with more detail than
just these individuals 64 data points so
here you can see I used another plot
this is also it could have been done
using the normal plot function this is
just to introduce you to some other of
MATLAB functions so plot 3 we plot the
the x and y coordinates and here are
plotting these Z coordinates as minus 1
which just plots the black dots behind
the red circles so if you just use a
plot2d function then you would just see
that the black dots would be on top of
the red circles which I just think looks
a little bit less nice so you can see it
would look like this it's basically the
same ok now what we are going to do is
compute the average activity at a an
arbitrary time point so I picked 100
milliseconds here we learned in a
previous video that this is the function
or one method that will allow us to
convert between the time point in
milliseconds that we want and the time
index so here we can we know that the
283rd time point in the EEG data
corresponds to a hundred milliseconds ok
and then we want to extract the average
data from this time point so we take
see data from all channels from this
time point from all trials and then we
take the mean over the third dimension
so that gives us the trial average this
particular interpolation function
requires that the input data the
double-precision or floating-point
precision and so the function double
here is just to make sure that that
whatever comes out of here will not
produce an air during interpolation okay
and so this try scattered interrupt this
is a MATLAB function that it provides us
with the function to compute
interpolation so now we're going to
interpolate over these grid points all
these black dots here to get a 100 by
100 map of interpolated points and the
100 by 100 comes from this parameter
here so you can change this you can try
saving it to a thousand or 10 and see
what the difference is okay so now that
we have our interpolated data we are
going to plot this interpolated data and
I'm just plotting it in a few different
ways just for comparison here I'm
plotting using the MATLAB function
contour F the F stands for filled here
using surf which stands for surface and
you can see that these appear to look
identical the only difference is with a
surface plot we are actually
representing this piece of data as a
surface as a landscape so you can see
that these edge values the microvolt
values are mapped here on to color what
I like about this representation is that
it helps you understand that these
features over multiple dimensions these
multi-dimensional feature spaces can be
conceptualized as
as landscapes as as a terrain so to
speak the contoured function that
actually is is just a flat function so
from when you're looking down of course
it's the same as a surface image using
the function image or image SC which
means it just does some color scaling
you can see two differences between
image and contour the first is that the
image function appears to be a bit more
pixelated whereas contour appears to be
a bit smoother and the second and more
important difference is that the
direction of the y axis is flipped so
here the red this red feature is on the
bottom and here it's on the top you can
see when you look at the y axis that it
really is the same data this is just
flipped image by default shows in X
sorry i J coordinates instead of X Y
coordinates so it just has these smaller
numbers at the top it doesn't really
matter whether use image or contour but
it is important always to remember that
image is going to flip the y axis
relative to contour this is very
important when plotting time frequency
plots because you want to make sure that
you are labeling the y axis correctly
right you don't want to have the lower
plot the lower frequencies on the bottom
but you mistakenly think that the lower
frequencies on top or vice-versa it's
easy to get confused so you just always
have to make sure that you're careful
with the image se in this figure you see
the interpolated data using the EEG lab
toolbox function called topo plot so you
can see these it shows the same data but
of course they've added all these other
nice features like the the circle for
the head and locations of the ears and
the nose and things another difference
you can see is that eg labtop oplot
function is using a different
interpolation function they use one
called grid data here i used one called
trice
interpret the difference is that this
function try scattered interval only
does interpolation it doesn't do
extrapolation and what that means is
that here is the boundary where we
recorded our data and anything within
this boundary would be interpolation
anything outside this boundary is
actually we it's not possible to
interpolate because there's nothing to
interpolate to so instead estimating a
point out here would be extrapolation
and so you can see that these values are
all ni n so they just don't exist
because these would be extrapolated
points with this grid data function it's
doing both interpolation and
extrapolation so it's it's also just
another difference to keep in mind so I
hope that helps you understand and be
able to interpret where topographical
maps come from and how data can be
represented from multiple channels over
space